In this 5-part series,
I look at the history, benefits,
and safety of water fluoridation,
and why I changed
my mind about it.
"Why Is There Fluoride in Water?
Is It Effective?"
A meta-analysis
of all the studies
on the dental health
implications
of vegetarian diets
showed significantly
fewer decayed teeth,
missing teeth,
and the number of teeth
with fillings.
One of the studies
that bucked the trend
and showed that
vegetarians had more cavities
blamed the excess decay
on the fact that vegetarians
were significantly
less likely to choose
fluoride-containing toothpaste,
supported by the fact
that those who did use
toothpaste with fluoride
had significantly fewer
decayed teeth
than those who didn't.
Fluoride is thought to protect
teeth by improving the intrinsic
stability of the mineral
structure of dental enamel.
A recent meta-analysis of nearly
100 randomized controlled trials
of fluoride toothpaste involving
more than 10,000 people
found "high-certainty" evidence
that toothpaste containing
the typical amount of fluoride
reduces tooth decay
significantly more
than non-fluoride toothpaste
in both children and adults.
But what about the addition
of fluoride to the water supply?
A medical consensus
of public health authorities
around the world
has considered
water fluoridation
at appropriate levels
as a safe and effective means
to prevent cavities
on a community-wide scale.
In fact, the CDC,
the US Centers for Disease
Control and Prevention,
deemed fluoridation
of drinking water
as one of the top ten
public health achievements
of the 20th century.
However, community
water fluoridation
has long been a flashpoint
of polemic and polarization.
Anti-fluoridation activists
underscore that there is
no human dietary
requirement for fluoride
and argue that
water fluoridation
isn't effective enough
to justify the costs,
which may include health risks.
First, some background before
I dive into the controversy.
Fluoride is a mineral element
in the Earth's crust
that naturally occurs
in most water supplies.
This is one of the reasons
fluoridation has withstood
Constitutional challenges.
Courts have ruled that,
rather than an added medication,
fluoride can be seen as
a nutrient found naturally
in some areas but not others,
and fluoridation
of water supplies
is a matter of just
leveling the playing field,
particularly for
poor communities
who may have limited access
to dental care.
Fluoridation can be defined as
"the upward
or downward adjustment
of the level of fluoride
content in drinking water
to an optimal level
just enough to prevent cavities
but not enough
to cause fluorosis,"
or cosmetic changes
to the teeth.
It all started in 1901
with an investigation
into Colorado Brown Stain,
"grotesque" brown stains
on the teeth
of Colorado Springs residents.
At the same time, teeth
afflicted by the condition were
"surprisingly and inexplicably
resistant to decay."
After fluoride was identified
as the basis for these changes,
a nationwide survey of fluoride
levels in drinking water
in the 1930s
led to the discovery
that fluoride could reach levels
around 1 part per million
without causing
serious fluorosis.
Hoping to get
the best of both worlds,
Grand Rapids, Michigan, in 1945,
became the first city
in the world
to fluoridate its water supply.
Within 11 years, cavity rates
among children in Grand Rapids
were reportedly down
more than 60 percent,
and a fluoridation
movement was born.
Today, about two dozen countries
fluoridate their drinking water.
Dozens of others have
naturally fluoridated water
or instead add fluoride
to milk or table salt.
Fluoridation pushback
started almost immediately
in the United States.
The obsession
of Dr. Strangelove's
Colonel Ripper with the purity
of his "precious bodily fluids"
was based on real-life
right-wing Red Scare
conspiracy theories
that fluoridation
was meant to produce
"moronic, atheistic slaves"
who would bow to the communists.
Today's social media
is also rife
with anti-fluoridation messages.
Studies have found that 63
percent of Instagram posts
regarding fluoride could be
classified as anti-fluoride,
64 percent of tweets on Twitter,
99 percent of YouTube videos,
and up to 100 percent
of fluoride groups and pages
found on Facebook
were anti-fluoride.
Years before COVID,
the antifluoridation crusade
was considered a case study
of "digital pandemics of
public health misinformation."
In the year before COVID,
the first worldwide survey
of the crisis of confidence
in science
of 140,000 people
in 140 countries
found that only
18 percent of humanity
appeared to have a "high" level
of trust in science.
To my pleasant surprise though,
despite so many
institutional failures,
a 2020 follow-up of the survey
found trust in science
actually increased after COVID.
Where does the science land
on water fluoridation?
First, let me address efficacy.
The CDC attributes the steep
decline in dental decay
in the United States in the
latter half of the 20th century
to water fluoridation,
but similar declines were noted
in non-fluoridated countries,
attributed in large part to the
widespread global distribution
of fluoride toothpaste.
The best evidence we have
comes from prospective studies
with concurrent controls,
comparing cavity rates over time
in fluoridated versus
non-fluoridated populations.
There have been more than 100
such studies to date,
and overall,
fluoridation results in
35 percent fewer decayed,
missing, or filled baby teeth
and 26 percent fewer
decayed, missing,
or filled permanent teeth.
So, community fluoridation
does indeed help
to cut down on cavities.
The question then becomes,
at what cost,
which we'll discuss next.